我们直接聊你的故事吧。你
Let's jump to your story. I mean, you
从小就特别聪明，打
got it came up always really smart like
数学奥赛那种。带我们回到
math olympiad like jump us to, you know,
那时候的 Alex。你当时
the Alex of that time. Like, what were
在想什么？感受是什么？
you feeling? What were you thinking? And
是什么把你推上这条路的？
what drove you down this road?
好，我
Yeah, I am
呃
uh
我在新墨西哥州长大，
Well, I grew up in New Mexico, Los
洛斯阿拉莫斯，现在因为
Alamos, New Mexico, um which now
《奥本海默》出名了，但
Oppenheimer famous, but um
那地方真的是穷乡僻壤
it really was the middle of nowhere and
呃
uh
我记得我参加了各种数学
I remember I did all these math
竞赛，各种计算机
competitions, all these um computer
竞赛，但那时候
science competitions, but then um
我知道自己想干大事，
I knew I wanted to do really big things
可又不清楚具体怎么干，
and it was like not exactly clear how or
到底该走哪条路。
what the exact path to do that would be.
嗯
Um
我有个朋友特别迷
and I had a friend who was really into
编程，高中毕业后
programming um and, you know, after high
就去硅谷实习了。
school got an internship in the valley.
他第一份实习好像是在
I think his first internship was at
Palantir。他
Palantir. And um and he, you know, he
算是影响了我，
was kind of this um influence for me and
所以我高中毕业后
so after I finished uh high school, I
就去了硅谷这边的
ended up working at Quora um here in
Quora 工作。然后
Silicon Valley. And then um
我在那干了一年，算是 gap
I worked there for a year. I took a gap
一年去工作，然后才去
year to work there um and then I went to
MIT。
MIT.
我在 Quora 工作时 19 岁，
Um and this is I was 19 when I worked at
去 MIT 时 18 岁，
Quora, I was 18 when I went to MIT and I
创办 Scale 时 19 岁。我
was 19 when I started um Scale. And I
记得 17 到 19 岁这段时间
remember this period from like 17 to 19
我
it was um
呃
uh
感觉自己一直在变，
I felt like I was constantly changing
就是
like
我到底想做什么
you know exactly what I want to do was
一直在变。我从身边的人
constantly changing. You know, I was
身上学到特别多，
learning so much just from the people
那种感觉就像
around me and it was just like I felt
一直在用消防栓
like I was drinking from the firehose
灌水一样。
pretty constantly during that time. Um
我特别推荐
and um I would definitely recommend you
两件事，它们
know the two things that were really
真的很重要。第一，去
important. One is I think working at a
公司工作非常有价值，因为
company was really valuable because like
从外面看，你根本不知道
I think from the outside in you have no
公司是怎么运转的。你不知道
idea how companies work. You have no
真正把一个东西
idea what it looks like to actually
做出来是什么样。你不知道
build something. You have no idea what
迭代一个东西是什么样。
it looks like to iterate on something.
你不知道一群人
You have no idea what it looks like for
一起做决定是什么样。
groups of people to make decisions. And
所以我觉得这很重要。
so I thought that was really important.
第二，去 MIT 上学
And then going to school at MIT was
也真的很重要，因为它
actually really important because it
给了我很多机会
just gave me a lot of um opportunity to
去探索什么东西有意思。
explore what was interesting. And so it
就是在 MIT 我开始训练
was at MIT that I started training my
第一批模型，
first models and um that I like played
玩那年刚出的
around with TensorFlow which had just
TensorFlow，也是在那
come out that year at MIT and where I
最终想出了 Scale
like ultimately came up with the idea of
这个点子。在 MIT 一年后我
Scale. And then after one year at MIT I
申请了 YC。
applied to YC.
当时能进 YC，感觉
You know, it felt like kind of like a
像个奇迹。
miracle to get in at that time. And uh
对，我的故事到那时
um yeah, that was I think the story till
就是这样，19 岁创办 Scale，
then I was 19 started Scale and uh the
后面的事大家都知道了。
rest is history.
你当时跟 Jared
I guess with uh you work with Jared
Friedman 一起，而且你带来的
Friedman at the time and um you came in
点子，跟最后的 Scale
with actually a very different idea than
完全不是一回事。
what ended up becoming Scale.
对，我们当时想做一个
Yeah, so we wanted to build um like an
AI agent，说来好笑，是
AI agent funnily enough for uh for doc
帮人获取医疗
for to help people like get medical
服务的。这个点子
care. Um and it was like the right it
是个很好的例子，我觉得
was a great example of an idea that I
它最终一定会实现。
think will ultimately exist. Like I
现在已经能看到了，帮人
think we're even seeing it now. Like AI
看病的 AI agent
agents to help people get medical care
非常真实。但当时
are very real. But it was the wrong
时机不对。
timing.
我们做了大概
Um and uh and we worked on it for about
一两个月，Jared 把我们
a month or two before Jared pulled us
拉到一边说，「兄弟们，
aside and were like, "Guys, this is I
我不确定这东西
don't know if this is going to go
能有什么前途。」
anywhere."
这正是我们
Um and uh and that's exactly what we
需要听到的话。那时候
needed to hear. And it was at that time
我已经把 AI
when like, you know, where I had studied
研究透了，也训练过模型，
AI to my T. I had like trained models
于是我们回到
and we thought we sort of went back to
起点，认真想了
the drawing board, thought deeply about
机会到底在哪，
where the opportunity was, and
想出了 Scale。
came up with Scale.
当时卖数据，
I guess selling data at the time, you
大语言模型
know, large language models were not
还没有冒头。
even had had not really come to the fore
但自动驾驶正在
yet. Um but self-driving cars were sort
兴起，计算机视觉
of coming up and and computer vision
突然火了。那算是
suddenly became So that was sort of the
第一个市场，对吧？
first market. Is that right?
对，
Yeah, so
事情是这样的，
the the story here is that like I was
我在 MIT 的时候做了
when I was at MIT, I did a bunch of
一堆项目，训练各种
projects like train train models of
模型。跟今天比，
various forms. And these were like, you
那些都是
know, by comparison today, they're like
小玩具模型。我记得
little toy models. And um and I remember
要训练一个模型，需要
to train a model, uh I needed three
三样东西。需要一个
things. I needed a
GCP 账号，就是云服务
uh GCP account, like I needed an account
账号，用来拿算力。
on some cloud service to get compute. I
需要能跑起来的代码，
needed um the code to run to actually
用来训练模型。还需要数据，
train the model. And I needed data. I
需要一个数据集。这三样里
needed a data set. And uh for two out of
有两样，你在网上
these three things, you could just press
点个按钮就能拿到。
a button online and get them. And then
可最后一样，数据，
for the last one, for data, there was
根本没有有效的办法
like no effective way to get data for
拿到训练用的数据。
training these training these models. Um
所以当时感觉特别明显，
and so it felt incredibly obvious that
这就是未来，
this was going to be the future, that
一定会有一种办法，
there was going to be a way to um
可以说是点个按钮
you know, press a button so to speak and
就拿到数据。很好笑的是
get data. And uh it was very funny
因为
because
后来那些年，Scale
in the years that followed, like in the
最初的很多年里，数据
first many years of Scale, data was very
一直很不性感。每次
unsexy still. Um every time we would go
出去融资，哪怕我们
out to fundraise, even though our
数字很好，收入
numbers were great and we had great
很好，VC 和投资人
revenue, you know, VCs and investors
总是很怀疑。他们
would always be very skeptical. They'd
会说，「这生意
be like, "Oh, I don't know if this is a
靠谱吗？能长久吗？
good business. Does it have longevity?
能持续吗？」
Is it durable?" Um
我当时觉得很奇怪，但
and uh it was really weird to me, but
这些投资人没有一个
you know, none of the investors had ever
训练过模型。所以他们
trained a model. So, I guess they didn't
大概是没看懂。
really get it. Um
快进到今天，
and uh fast forward to today, you know,
我们融到了钱，
we we managed to raise money, we managed
一直撑着，生意
to keep going, managed to keep growing
一直在长，可当年
the business, but um the very same
放弃我们、
investors who passed on us and were um
看衰 AI 前景的那批投资人，
were very dour on the potential of AI
今天在写文章，讲
are writing think pieces today about how
数据多么关键，是 AI
data is so critical and is one of the
最大的商业机会之一。
biggest business opportunities um in AI.
看着这一切兜了一圈
So, uh it's very funny to see that whole
回来，挺好笑的。
whole thing come full circle.
我觉得关键是，你
Yeah, I think the the key thing is you
得对一套没人同意的
need to develop conviction in a set of
信念，建立起信念。
beliefs that nobody else um agrees with.
你看世界上
Like, I think if you look at all the
最成功的那些公司，
most successful companies in the world,
嗯
um
它们起步的时候，
they were started at a time long before
核心想法离流行还远得很。
the sort of like core idea was popular.
他们就埋头做，
And they work on that. They toil in
默默无闻地熬很多年，
obscurity for years and years before,
直到这个想法、这个领域、
you know, the the idea or the space or
这门生意的概念
the concept of the business, you know,
变成共识。你能成功的
becomes consensus. And the only way
唯一办法，就是
you're going to be successful is if
能早早看出这些
you're able to identify these truths
关于世界的真相，比所有人
about the world early, long before
都早。我觉得
everyone else. And I think the like
最让人意外的一点是，
I mean, one of the most surprising
Scale 做 AI
things like, you know, Scale, we've been
做了十年。
working on AI for a decade. You know,
你不能根据身边
you just you can't base your business
所有人在说什么
decisions based on what everyone else is
来做商业决定。你要是
saying around you. Like, if you go too
太跟着大流走，就会
much with the herd, you will get
彻底迷糊，最后
immensely confused and you will end up
哪儿也到不了。所以你得建立
nowhere. And so you have to develop your
自己的罗盘，判断未来
own compass of what you think the future
会是什么样，
is going to look like
因为其他人只会
because everyone else will just confuse
把你搞糊涂。
you.
没有人在创业的时候
nobody is good at starting a company
就已经擅长创业。
when they start a company.
然后
And
我记得跟很多
I remember talking to a lot of the
早期认识的投资人聊，
investors who I met very early on and
他们很多人会说，
they you know, a lot of them would say
「你长得太快了，
like oh, like you know, you just grew so
变得也太快，
quickly and you changed so quickly and
我当时
like I didn't you know, I didn't see it
完全没看出来。」我觉得
at the time. And I think that's probably
每个创业的人
true for literally everyone who starts a
都是这样，没有人
company like nobody is
擅长一件自己
nobody is good at something they've
从没做过的事，对吧？所以
never done before, right? And so
我觉得所有创业者，一开始
I think for all entrepreneurs, you start
干什么都很烂，
out pretty shitty at everything and
整场游戏就是你怎么
the whole game is how do you develop
把自己练出来，不断进步，
yourself to continuously improve to get
快速学习。
better and learn quickly.
你觉得今天在 AI
What do you think it's like to start a
时代创业，
company today with with AI in the age of
是什么样的？
AI?
嗯。
Yeah.
我真的觉得我们
I mean I really think I think we're at
正处在一个了不起的时刻，
this like in amazing moment in the world
瓶颈不再是 AI 模型
where the bottleneck is not the progress
的进步，瓶颈是
of the AI models, the bottleneck is
把它扩散到世界
diffusing that through the rest of the
的其他角落，帮世界适应
world and and helping the world adapt to
这项已经存在的
this amazing technology that already
了不起的技术。就算模型
exists. Like I think if the models
从今天起不再进步，
didn't improve at all from today, there
接下来几十年
would still be like decades and decades
经济、世界的运转方式、
of like total upheaval and change in the
我们身边的一切，
economy and how the world operates and
依然会天翻地覆。
and everything around us and um you
所以我觉得，这
know, so I think it's as a result, it's
是最不可思议的，
like one of the most incredible it's
大概是文明级别的
probably a like once in a civilization
一次机会，去做梦想家，
opportunity to be a dreamer and to have
去有愿景，有野心，
a vision and to have ambition and to
去用做出了不起的东西，
impose a view of how the future world
把你对未来世界的看法
should look by building something
强加给世界。
amazing. Um you know, one of the things
我们之前在
that we were we were chatting about um
呃
uh
后台聊到，
you know, backstage is you know, when
我创办 Scale 那会儿，十
when I started Scale or you know, 10
年前，你要创业，
years ago, if you start a company, you
那是大卫
had to be um you know, it was like David
对歌利亚，你得聪明，
versus Goliath and you had to be clever
得找到一个切入
and you had to find like an angle into
市场的角度，还得
the market and you had to sort of like,
想办法去竞争，
you know, figure out um a way to compete
哪怕你的资源
even though you had much fewer
少得多。而现在我觉得，有了
resources. And now I actually think with
agent 和整个 AI
the power of agents um and AI broadly
的力量，更像是歌利亚
speaking, it's much closer to Goliath
对歌利亚。或者说
versus Goliath. Like I think but maybe
创业公司是机甲歌利亚，
the startup is like a mecha Goliath that
被 agent 和 AI 的力量
is like vastly enhanced by the power of
大幅强化了，而
agents and AI and you know, the the
大公司算是
large companies are the sort of like
传统款的歌利亚。
more traditional Goliath, so to speak.
我觉得现在的创业公司，
But I think that startups now like if
只要真正拥抱 AI agent，
you properly embrace AI agents and um
想明白怎么用最有野心的
figure out the way to leverage their
方式发挥它们的长处，
strengths in the most like ambitious
你就能轻松干掉
ways, you can easily outcompete
老牌巨头。
incumbents.
我们聊聊超级智能吧，
So, let's talk about super intelligence
这个词都写进
because that's clearly that's even in
你们实验室的名字里了。
the name of your lab.
嗯，
Um,
在今天的 Meta 内部，超级智能
what does super intelligence mean
具体意味着什么？
operationally inside Meta right now?
一年前
Yeah, I think that you know, we a year
Mark 写了一份
ago Mark wrote this um,
关于个人超级智能的备忘录，
memo about personal super intelligence,
我觉得跟你说的
which I think actually is very similar
个人 AGI 很像。
to your concept of personal AGI. But,
我们相信，世界上
you know, we believe that everybody in
每一个人，几十亿人，
the world, you know, all the billions of
都会有一个
people in the world are going to have a
为自己量身定制的
super intelligence that is adapted and
超级智能，帮他们
tailored to them, that is enables them
达成目标，了解他们的
to accomplish their goals, knows their
处境，最终扩展
context, and ultimately is an expander
他们自己的能动性。我们
of their own agency. Like I think the
想得最多的一件事，就是
thing that we think a lot about is is
能动性扩展。怎么帮人
agency expansion. How do we help people
做成以前
accomplish things that they couldn't
想都不敢想的事？如果
have ever dreamed of before? And what
一切都变得容易了，
would everyone in the world do if
每个人会去做什么？我们
everything was just easy? Um, and we
也从生态的角度
think about this in a in an ecosystem
看这件事。
way um, as well. I think uh, you know,
Patrick 提到过，我们
Patrick mentioned it, but you know, we
不相信那种一统天下的、
don't believe in this totalizing, you
极权式的看法，
know, totalitarian view of, you know,
说 AI 会控制世界。我们相信
AIs that control the world. We believe
AI 会强化这个
that these are going to enhance this
非常广阔的生态。所以
very broad ecosystem. And so, you know,
我们相信全世界几十亿人
we believe in billions of people all
都会有自己的
around the world all having their own
个人超级智能。我们也
personal super intelligence. And we also
相信创业
believe in, you know, an explosion of
会爆发。今天 Meta 的
entrepreneurship. There's 200 million
平台上有两亿
businesses that uh, are on Meta's
家企业。我们觉得这个数字
platforms today. We think that number
应该涨到几十亿，靠的是
should go to billions with this
创造力的爆发和 AI
explosion of of creativity and using AI
工具。最终我们觉得，
tools. And ultimately we think that, you
会形成一个动态的
know, it's going to be this like dynamic
生态，企业 agent 和
ecosystem of business agents working
个人 agent 协作，
with, you know, personal agents and
发展出一个
developing this sort of like
复杂的、完全由 AI
uh, complex ecosystem that is fully AI
加持的生态。
supercharged.
运营一个前沿
how you know, how how has running a
实验室，感觉怎么样？
frontier lab been? Um, you know, the
嗯，
Yeah, yeah.
我在 Meta
So, I think it was um, it's been you
差不多一年了，
know, I've been at Meta for about a year
这一年
now and it's been um,
很不寻常。
quite a year. I think uh,
进去的时候，
you know, getting in and um, you know,
我们公开讲过，
Meta we we've talked about it publicly
Llama 4 没有走在
like Llama 4 wasn't on the trajectory
Meta 需要的轨道上，所以
that was needed for um, for Meta and so
我进去之后，我们
I got in there and we kind of did a
从零开始想，怎么
zero-based build of how do you um,
建一个完整的前沿实验室，
you know, build an entire frontier lab
呃
uh,
某种程度上是从头建，
you know, in some ways kind of from
当然用了很多已有的东西，
scratch obviously using a lot of what we
而且要尽可能快。
had um, and move as quickly as possible.
九个月之后，
And so within nine months of that moment
我们发布了 Muse Spark 1，两
we launched Muse Spark 1 and then uh, two
个月后又发布了 Muse Image
months later we launched Muse Image and
和 Muse Spark 1.1。
Muse Spark 1.1 and um,
这里面有几件事
you know, there's a few things that I
让我印象很深。
think have really struck me about this.
第一，人才密度
It you know, the first is talent density
极其重要。那是
was incredibly important. That was the
最核心的一注。
the core thing to bet on and um,
人才密度这东西
like talent density is something that
会自然复利。你手里
compounds naturally. Like the more
人才越多，最顶尖的
talented people you have the more of the
人才就越想
most most talented people want to join
加入你。
you. Um,
从内部看，这
you know, in and I think it's it's kind
挺神奇的，
of um, amazing to see on the inside but
就是
you know,
前沿 AI 工作是研究，
frontier AI work is research. Like we
是科学工作。我们在
are it is scientific work. We're
探索这些模型能做什么？
exploring what can you do with these
怎么把它们推到极限？
models? How can you push these models?
它们能做到的边界
What is the what are the reaches of what
在哪里？这需要
can be accomplished with these models
一套完全不同的
which requires a totally different
思路和运作模式，
mindset and operating model than you
跟互联网公司、
know, existed for internet companies or
互联网产品那套不一样。
internet products and what not. There's
更多的是实验，
a lot more about experimentation, about
是科学，是规模化，
science, about scaling and everything
最终一切都归结为怎么建
ultimately is about how do you develop
一个实验室、一套运作模式、
a lab, an operating model, a system that
一个系统，能跟着生态里
will just um, be able to compound with
所有的指数增长
all of the exponential growth that will
一起复利。既包括
happen in the ecosystem. Both the
能力的指数增长，
exponential growth in capabilities, the
算力的指数增长，
exponential growth in compute, um, the
采用和使用量的
exponential growth in adoption and
指数增长。我们正处在
usage. Like these are all um, we are on
一条非常非常陡的指数曲线上，
this like very, very steep exponent
生态的每一个维度
across maybe every dimension of the
几乎都是。所以重要的是
ecosystem. And um, it's important to
把实验室培养成
develop like a like an organism. That's
一个有机体，我是这么看的，
how I think about the lab that that's
它得能跟着一起长。
able to sort of grow with that. Um, you
听起来其中一个办法，
I mean, it sounds like one of the ways,
我自己用
I mean, certainly when I was using uh,
Muse Spark 配 Open Claw 的时候，
Muse Spark with my Open Claw, like, it
很明显它跟
it became clear that it was as good as
Opus 一样好，尤其是
Opus, especially for that sort of
带 skill 文件的 agent 流程，但它
agentic flow with skill files, but it
便宜了八倍。
was like eight x cheaper, actually.
对。这正是
Yes. Well, we I think this this goes to
重点。我们不
it. Like, I don't, you know, we don't
相信一个模型贵到
believe in a world where these models
只有最有钱的
are so expensive that, you know, they
开发者和公司
get rationed only for the most wealthy
才用得起的世界。
of developers and and companies. Um,
重要的是每个人都能
it's important for everyone to be able
用上这项技术，
to use the technology to um, and to
用它做出自己想做的
build whatever they want to build with
任何东西。我们
it. And I think that, you know, we take
的看法是，
a view
最好的 AI 产品
I think the best AI products haven't
还没被做出来。
even been developed yet. You know, that
你看 AI 生态
if you look at the AI ecosystem and
发生的一切，每一波
everything that's happened, like every
都比上一波
wave is 10 times bigger than the past
大十倍。我创办
wave. So, you know, when I started
Scale 的时候，第一波大概是
scale, the first wave was maybe
自动驾驶。自动驾驶
self-driving cars. Self-driving cars are
很棒，真的
really awesome. They're like really,
很酷，但跟大语言模型
really cool, but that was like pales in
和聊天机器人一比
comparison to large language models and
就小巫见大巫了。聊天机器人
chatbots. And like, you know, chatbots
大概比自动驾驶
became this thing that was like probably
又大了
10 times bigger even than um than uh you
十倍。再后来
know, self-driving cars. And then there
几年出了
were coding agents which came a few
编程 agent，编程 agent
years later. And coding agents are
大概又比聊天机器人
probably 10 times bigger than than um
大十倍。我觉得我们就在
chatbots. And I think we're just on this
这条陡峭的曲线上，
steep curve. Like, we're going to keep
会不断看到新的模态、
seeing these new modalities and form
新的形态、AI 范式
factors and developments of the AI
的新发展，每一个都比
paradigm that will each be dramatically
上一个大得多。所以
bigger than the last. And so, um you
我们的看法是，
know, our point of view is like, let's
把生态放开，
let's unleash the ecosystem. Let's
去探索，去看，去建，
explore and let's see um let's build,
一起建出
you know, kind of the future of the
未来的世界。
world together.
我真心相信这些
but there's like I truly believe these
模型已经
these models are already just incredibly
强大得不得了。它们
powerful. Like they should they should
应该强到能推动
be so powerful to fuel, you know, um
GDP 增长
many many points of expansion of GDP
好几个百分点，剩下的就看
growth and I think it's like up to smart
有愿景有野心的聪明人
people with vision and ambition to make
去把它变成现实。
all that happen.
我问一个问题。
Let's see. So, one question. I mean,
回头看这十年，
when you look back on the decade, um
你觉得关于 AI，有什么
what do you think they'll say was
事后看很明显、
obvious in hindsight about AI that
但现在的人
people are just missing in real time
正在错过的？
right now?
现在很多争论
You know, so much of the debate that
都在吵，模型
happens these days is around oh, how
到底在变多好，
good are the models actually getting and
模型能不能跨过某个
can the models actually bridge this
坎，什么时候
issue and, you know, when are we going
会有超级智能？是
to get super intelligence? Is that in
两年还是五年？
like 2 years or 5 years? And, you know,
会不会撞墙？
are we going to hit a wall? And, you
这些争论
know, so much of that debate is like
我觉得某种程度上
I think um in some ways uh
有点浪费时间，因为
a little bit of a waste of time because,
嗯
you know,
我觉得我们一定会有
I think it's inevitable that we're going
非常强大的模型，
to have very powerful models and um you
与其这样，
know, rather than
我们回头会说，「哦，
I think we'll look back and say, "Oh,
当年吵它到底什么时候
all this arguing around like when
发生，其实
exactly it was going to happen was sort
挺短视的，因为
of um was short-sighted because the
现实是，整个人类
reality is we are just as a entire human
文明都在这条不可思议的
civilization on this incredible
指数曲线上。你看过去十年
exponential. Like you cannot look at the
AI 的进步，
progress of AI over the past decade and
不可能不被它走了多远
not just be totally awestruck by how far
震住。十年前，最好的
it's come. Like a decade ago, the best
AI 模型只能在 YouTube 视频里
AI models could recognize cats in
认出猫。而现在，我们在跟
YouTube videos. And now, you know, we're
呃
talking to
一个数字神明说话，它能
um you know, a digital god that can, you
嗯
know,
我们都见过那些
uh I mean, we've all seen some of the
黑客操作，见过这些系统
hacks and some of the some of the things
能做到的事。
these systems are capable of. And
你只能被震住。
you just can't help but be awestruck.
我觉得这个趋势
And and I think this trend will just
会继续。这些模型
continue. Like these these models are
会越来越强。
going to become more and more powerful.
所以，
And so,
十年后回头看，会很明显，
I think a decade looking back, it'll
智能变得
it'll be obvious that intelligence
充裕了，能动性也
became abundant and that agency became
充裕了。我们现在的趋势
abundant. Like the current trends we're
会一直继续下去。
on are just going to keep continuing.
这会很奇怪。
And um this will be very strange. I
在人类历史上，
mean, I think for the history of
嗯
humanity, um
一群聪明人聚在一起
you know, groups of smart people getting
朝一个共同目标努力，
together towards a shared goal was was
一直是进步的瓶颈。
the bottleneck of progress. You know, US
美国某种意义上
The United States of America in some
就是个例子。
sense was an example of this. Like the
美国就是由
United States of America was formed from
一群非常聪明的人
a smart group of very smart people
聚在一起，带着他们想实现的
getting together and having a vision for
未来愿景建立起来的。
the future that they wanted to enact.
美国几乎每家公司
And that's the story of nearly every
都是这个故事，
company um in America. And it's the
每家 YC 公司也是。
story of every YC company. Um
而
and
这要变了。突然之间，
that's going to change. Like all of a
稀缺的资源不再是
sudden, the scarce resource isn't going
智能或能动性。我真的
to be intelligence or agency. I really
觉得会是愿景和
think it's going to be vision and
野心。就是说，你有没有
ambition. It's like, do you have a clear
一个清晰的看法，
view of
你想让未来的世界
what you want the world to look like in
长什么样？你想用哪一种
the future? What is the like one way in
方式，在世界未来
which you want to put your finger on the
的走向上
scale for how the future of the world
按下你的手指，让五到
will develop and how the how the world
十年后的世界
will look like in 5 to 10 years that it
跟今天不一样？你有没有
does not look like today? And do you
野心和动力，去
have the ambition and drive to like go
趟过所有的烂事，把它
through all the crap to make that
实现？AI 会让这更容易。
happen? And AI will make that easier.
AI 里的 agent 让这件事比十年前
Like agents in AI makes that maybe 10
容易十倍甚至
times or 100 times easier than it was a
一百倍。但反过来，
decade ago. But the flip side of that is
你突然就可以
then you all of a sudden you can dream
做更大的梦。而这个世界
bigger. Like I think And the world is
嗯
like
还有太多东西
um you know, there's so many things that
需要演进，我们才能
need to evolve for us to be able to
完全拥抱这项技术。
fully embrace this technology. Um you
今天的世界
know, the world is like really just, you
其实根本没准备好
know, barely even ready for this
迎接这项技术。我觉得
technology today. And I think, you know,
作为建造者，我们有责任
as a builder, we have a responsibility
让世界做好准备。我们
to prepare the world, right? Like we
得帮企业和
have to help enterprises and
政府适应这项
governments, you know, to adapt to this
新技术。我们得想清楚，
new technology. We have to help figure
从生物安全、
out how we secure the world from a
网络安全的角度
biosecurity perspective or cybersecurity
怎么守住这个世界。得想清楚
perspective. We have to figure out how
怎么管理这项新技术
we um how we're going to to manage all
带来的所有
these risks that we see with this new
风险。但反过来，这
technology. But on the flip side, it's
也是人类
also the time of like, you know,
前所未有的机会。
unprecedented opportunity for humans.
我们能发展新的科学，能
Like we can develop new sciences. We can
解决健康和生物领域
solve problems in health and biology
一直没解决的问题。能
that have been forever unsolved. We can
建立以前想都
build new businesses that you couldn't
想不到的新企业。还有
have even imagined before. There's like
以前不可能存在的
new creative opportunities that couldn't
新的创作机会。所以
have existed before. So, it's like
这是一个不可思议的、
it's just this incredible cradle of of
机会和风险并存的摇篮，
opportunity and risks that uh that I
我觉得没有比现在更好的时候，
think makes it like no better time to be
去做一个建造者，
someone who's a builder and um
带着强烈的看法，
and has a strong view of how the world
去改变世界。
should change.
你觉得路径变了吗？
Do you think the path has changed? I
我看到一个数据，
mean, one of the things I saw, I think
斯坦福的计算机
Stanford uh the amount of computer
专业人数降了
science majors actually dropped by some
两位数的百分比。大家
double-digit percentage. It's people
有点担心，这在我看来
sort of worried like, which is sort of
挺疯的。你还是
insane to me. Like you still sort of
需要那些技能，才能做出
need those skills to even create agents
那么好的 agent。也许以后
that are that good. Maybe that won't be
不是这样了，我不确定。
true. I'm not really sure.
你有没有变？
How you know, have you changed you know,
你会对今天在场的人
what do you what would you say to people
说什么？这是
in this audience right now? Like this is
大家真实面对的
sort of a real question that people are
问题。他们该变成
sort of facing. Like should they become
文科脑，少一点理科脑吗？
more word cell and less shape rotator?
该怎么走？还有
Like what you know, what's the move? And
你
you
这有没有改变
has that changed um
你想招的人，
the kind of people you're looking to
和你现在在 Meta
hire and, you know, how you manage your
管团队的方式？
teams right now at Meta?
我觉得系统化、严谨的思考
I think systematic and rigorous thinking
依然极其重要，因为
are still incredibly important because
抽象层，
you know, the abstraction layer, I mean,
我以前不相信事情
I didn't used to believe that this is
会这么发展，但它
how it was going to play out, but it
真的发生了，抽象层
really has, like, the abstraction layer
一直在变。我
just keeps changing. So, you know, when
当年创业的时候，我们
I started a company back in my day, we
写代码。
wrote code. Um
现在我相信在座的
And now, you know, I'm sure nobody here
没人再写代码了，太离谱了。
writes code anymore. That's ridiculous.
但现在变成了，你怎么
But um but now it's about how do you
把 agent 编排到一起？
orchestrate the agents together? And
然后是，你怎么建立
then it's like, how do you develop these
agent 的组织？怎么
organizations of agents? Like, how do
让一百万个 agent
you get like a million agents to work
好好协作？再往后，怎么
together well? And then it'll be, how do
让一万亿个 agent
you get like a trillion agents to work
好好协作？我觉得
together well? Like, I think that
会一直
there's going to be this continued um
需要想清楚，在我们
uh need to figure out how you structure
所处的抽象层上，
uh workflows at the abstraction layer
怎么组织工作流。
that we're going to be operating at. And
而这种严谨的系统化
that form of like rigorous systematic
思考，传统上
thinking, I mean, traditionally the way
在我创业的那个年代，
this would work like in my era of
是你先
starting companies is you would start by
写代码，然后有了
writing code, and then you would have
人的组织，再
organizations of humans, and you'd
想清楚怎么组织
figure out how you how to organize those
这些人。这需要系统
humans. Um and that requires systems
思维。现在可能更
thinking. And now, maybe it's like much
接近于，你先
more much closer to first you you
编排 agent，再想清楚
orchestrate the agent, then you figure
怎么编排成千上万的
out how to orchestrate like these armies
agent 大军。
of agents. But um
但我觉得系统思维永远
but I think systems thinking is never
不会过时。所以我觉得
going to go out of style. So, I think
全押文科脑
it's definitely a mistake to go all in
肯定是错的。你还是
on Word Cell. Like, I think you need to
得会理科脑那套。
you need to shape rotate. Um
但往后
but then I think the sort of like um
更需要的，
much more of I think what's necessary
我觉得是
going in the future is having um
一个更深的罗盘，一套
a deeper sort of compass and
关于世界该怎么发展的
philosophical view on how the world
哲学观。因为
should develop. Because I think there
人类历史上有很多很多
are there are many many lessons um from
教训，关于
human history around um
我们怎么看文明
how how we think civilization go through
走过这样的时期。
this period. And um
人类在接下来十年的变化，
So, you know, humanity will change more
大概会超过过去
in the next decade than it has in the
一百年。
past 100 years, probably. And um
所以我觉得，我们必须
And so, I think like the imperative for
对此有积极的愿景，
us to have positive visions for that and
并且能连贯地讲清楚
have coherent uh articulations of how
它该怎么发展，这比以往
that should develop are are more
任何时候都重要。
important than ever.
嗯
Um
我们具体一点。
Let's get a little more concrete. I
我好奇的是，
mean, one of the things I'm curious
有没有哪些 AI
about is like, are there sort of
应用，你在朋友
applications of AI that you're seeing
或者 Meta 内部看到的、
among your friends or internal to Meta
可以聊的，
that you can talk about that are, you
是近期很明显、
know, they're sort of obvious near-term
但大家还没想到的。
maybe people haven't figured out yet. I
给我们点内幕。
mean, give us some alpha.
嗯，
Um, I mean,
我觉得在
I think there's still just like
agent 循环上还有
astronomical opportunity in
天文数字级的机会，想清楚
uh agentic looping and and figuring out
怎么建一套系统，让你
how you develop systems that enable you
能多花一千倍、一百万倍
to spend like 1,000 x more or 1 million
的 token，在一个持续的
x more on tokens to drive an outcome in
反馈循环里推动一个结果。
a in a continuous feedback loop. Like if
你想想大多数公司，
you think about most companies,
公司本质上就是
companies are just these like
大规模的反馈循环，每一条边
large-scale feedback loops where humans
都由人来操作。
are operating each of the edges. Like,
公司获得
you know, companies they um, they get
客户，想办法让
customers and they figure out to make
客户更满意。
those customers happier. And if
客户更满意，就
customers are happier, then they spend
花更多钱。花更多钱，公司
more. And if they spend more, then they
就能雇更多人，再去
can hire more people who can then go
找更多客户，
figure out how to get more customers and
让客户更满意。这
make those customers happier. And that's
某种意义上
like this, you know, that in some sense
就是每家创业公司、
is the feedback loop of uh
每家企业的反馈循环。
of every startup or every business. And,
在这里面还有
you know, these within that there are
很多微型反馈循环。我
micro feedback loops that exist. And I
觉得开发 agent 系统
think developing agentic systems that
去运转和优化这些
can operate and optimize these feedback
反馈循环，里面有
loops is there's like just huge amounts
巨大的机会。我们
of of alpha there. Like I think we've
在 Meta 内部
seen internally at Meta um
看到过这样的案例，只要建对了
cases where if you can develop the right
agent 循环，有对的评估
agentic loop and you have the right eval
或者对的指标让 agent 去
or the right metric for the agents to
优化，一群 agent
optimize, you can have a swarm of agents
干的活能超过一个一百人
accomplish more than like a team of 100
的工程师团队，
engineers in, you know, uh
而且赢得非常非常
very very handily actually, very very
轻松。所以我觉得，想清楚
easily. And so, I think figuring out
这个世界
what the world
在有了大量
um looks like with lots of uh
这种
sort of this like um
agent 协作问题之后是什么样，
these agentic coordination problems, I
是今天最有意思的
think that is like one of the most
问题之一。那
interesting problems today. So,
具体操作上，就是 markdown
mechanically speaking, I mean, markdown
文件、cron 定时任务，
files, cron jobs, is I mean, is it
然后基本上把 agent
that's and then basically pointing the
指向足够多的数据，让它
agent at enough data so that it can
能搞明白一些
figure something out that, you know,
训练数据里没有的东西？
maybe isn't in distribution.
对，想清楚
Yeah, I think figuring out Yeah, yeah,
操作上指标
mechanically figuring out what the
是什么，然后就归结为
metric is and then yeah, it just comes
skills、markdown 文件、cron
down to skills, markdown files, cron
定时任务、
jobs,
/goal。
/goal.
对，/goal。我总觉得挺好笑，
Yeah, /goal. Like I think I think it's
真挖进去一看，一切
always funny how mundane everything is
都很平常。
once you really dig into it. But um
最后一个问题，
So I like to end on this, which is um
就是
you know,
你能给 18 岁的自己
you get a telegram to send to the
发一封电报，
18-year-old version of yourself, you
你现在会对那个人
know, what do you say to that person
说什么？顺便，
right now given all, you know, I mean,
谢谢你回来
thank you for coming back and sharing
跟大家分享。
your wisdom with this audience. I mean,
你现在会给 18 岁的自己
you know, what would you send in a
漂流瓶里
message in a bottle to the 18-year-old
装一句什么话？
version of yourself right now?
我觉得
Yeah, I think the
归根结底就是
I think it really boils down to
建立你自己内心的罗盘，
develop your own internal compass for
判断未来会怎么发展，
how you think the future will develop
并且对它有坚定的信念，
and have strong conviction in it
因为你会被
because, you know, you will get so you
噪音淹没，被各种人
will get inundated with noise and people
指指点点，会
telling you and like you'll could
非常困惑，非常
be very confusing and it'll be very
难。尤其你年轻、
hard. And especially when you're young
没经验的时候，
and you don't have experience like it
很难
can feel very difficult to
呃
um
对自己相信的、想做的事
have true conviction in what you believe
有真正的信念。但我觉得
and and what you want to do. But I think
这是最重要的事。就像
that's the most important thing. Kind of
我们前面聊的，
as we talked about, you know, um
正是对我们在做的事
it took a deep deep conviction in what
有极深的信念，才扛过了
we were building to be able to weather
很多年
the the sort of storms of many years of
呃
um of
市场、行业、
uh chaos in the market, in the industry,
身边人的混乱。
in the people around us. And so
另一条
um And and then the other piece of
建议是，去找
advice I would have is try to identify
这个世界上哪一条指数曲线
what is the what is the exponential in
既最陡，
the world that has both the steepest
又能走得最久。
curve and will go the longest. And you
几十年前这条曲线
know many decades ago this curve was
是摩尔定律，那大概
was Moore's law and that probably was
是
you know that was
当时显然该押注的东西。
at the time like clearly the right thing
现在我觉得是 AI
to invest on. I think right now it's AI
的进步，但未来还会有更多
progress but there will be more of these
这种很陡的曲线，而且
very steep curves in the future and it's
曲线的起点
fine if these curves start
很无聊，
you know the starting point is very
甚至看起来没什么意思，
boring or like it doesn't even seem that
都没关系。
interesting. Like it you know when we
当时
started
我刚开始做 Scale 的时候，
when I started working on scale
我们在 YouTube 视频里
you know we had cat detectors in YouTube
做猫检测器，很难
videos and that felt you know
跟人解释，说这
it's hard to say explain the story that
是我们这个时代
that's like the most important
最重要的技术，但它就在
technology of our time but it was on
一条难以置信的指数曲线上。
just this like unbelievable exponential.